[music]
[Instructor] Cool, so we have
our player set up
as much as possible
for now,
so in the past we've commonly
gotten just the gameObject
or the Transform Component,
whatever we wanted
to call any methods.
But if we want to actually
control the movement
and the Gravity of the player,
and all of that,
we actually need to use
a new way to get a Component
for our "Rigidbody,"
because Rigidbodies aren't
something that are automatically
on other gameObjects
versus something like a Transform,
which is always on gameObjects.
So we'll do that using
our PlayerController Script.
So in our PlayerController Script,
we're going to create
a new variable.
I already know that I don't need
this to be seen
by anything outside of this class,
so I'm going to name
this private for now.
And then, it's actually
going to be our Rigidbody.
So this will be the Rigidbody
Component on our Player
similar to how we had
attached gameObjects before
but in this case,
this is a Rigidbody.
And we're going to just
name this "playerRb,"
for Player Rigidbody.
Now versus something
like transform
where we can already get access
to our transform Component,
we don't automatically get access
to our Rigidbody Component
because that's not something
on every single gameObject.
So in order to do that,
we actually need to use
something called
"GetComponent<>()".
So if we take our playerRb
variable for our Rigidbody,
and now if we assign that or set
that to the Component of our Rigidbody,
so we use a method
called GetComponent<>().
Now we have to use these left
and right carets here,
which is different than using
parentheses to pass in parameters.
Specifically, the right and left carets
actually get you
a type of something,
so for example,
in this case we're getting a Rigidbody,
but you could use these carets
to find the type of anything,
so if we actually want
to get a Collider, for example,
that was on our Player,
we could do that too.
So the carets are specifically
for finding different things like...
our components that are
on our different objects.
Now we do need to close
this with a parentheses
because it is actually a call
that we're making as a method.
And we'll close that statement.
And then, just to test and see
if this works if we actually
got that Rigidbody,
we're going to apply
a force to our Rigidbody.
Now because we're using
a Rigidbody Component,
it already has a method
called "AddForce()."...
And you can think of this
similar as "Transform.Translate(),"
but instead of moving
something physically
just using positions,
we can apply forces to things
just like we would in the real world
using physics to make something move.
So in this case, we're going
to make our Player move up
just to see what happens,
so we're going to use "Vector3.up,"...
and we're going to amplify
this by a lot,
so we'll just multiply
this by 100.
And then we'll save,
and now in Unity
if you will look at our Game view,
when I press Play
the character jumped very slightly.
Let's see if we can make
that a little bit more powerful.
Let's set this to something like 1000.
And we'll save, and now back
in Unity we'll press Play.
There you go.
That's a lot of force.
And then because he has Gravity
the character falls all the
way back down to the ground.
We'll do that one more time.
Whoo! It's like he's so excited.
Cool.
So what you're going to do is going
into your PlayerController Script.
In your PlayerController
Script you're going to make
a private Rigidbody
variable called playerRb
for the player Rigidbody,
and then in your Start() method
you're going to assign that Rigidbody
to our Rigidbody Component using
the GetComponent<>() method,
so that it can find
the Rigidbody on the player,
and then we're going
to apply a force
to that Player so that we can
see that they're actually
jumping in the air using forces.
Now it's your turn. [music]